[Music]
start with a right triangle with legs of
length a
and b
and a hypotenuse of length c
the square drawn using the side of
length a has an area of a squared
similarly
the square drawn using the side of
length b has an area of b squared
and finally the square drawn using the
hypotenuse of length c has an area of c
squared
[Music]
then add two more copies of the right
triangle one reflected about the angle
between the legs and one rotated and
shifted to the bottom of the square off
of the hypotenuse
next we draw two lines of symmetry
separating two hexagons inside of the
diagram like this
[Music]
we use the new regions as follows
this top quadrilateral is congruent to
its reflection along the first line of
symmetry
the resulting quadrilateral is congruent
to its rotation of 90 degrees clockwise
about the left triangle vertex and this
quadrilateral is congruent by 180 degree
rotation to the other half of the second
hexagon cut by the second line of
symmetry
therefore the two overlapping hexagons
in the diagram are both built from two
copies of the same quadrilateral
that means that these two hexagons
doesn't close the exact same area
but notice that both of these hexagons
use two copies of the original right
triangle
so removing those triangles from both
diagrams shows that the large square
encloses the exact same area as the two
smaller squares which means that c
squared is the same as a squared plus
b squared
[Music]
remembering that a and b
are the lengths of two legs of a right
triangle with hypotenuse of length c
we have shown that for such a right
triangle c squared is equal to a squared
plus
b squared
this is the pythagorean theorem
as proved by da vinci
[Music]
you